Chodesh a second day and today's דף daf, *daf* is דף ל"ד
*daf Lamed Daled* and we pick up and we're actually at the
top of ל"ד *Lamed Daled*. Let me refresh what we said at
the end of yesterday and tell you also what תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
adds to make it a little more understandable.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had been dealing with the whole issue about
where is your עירוב eruv *eruv* and is it in a place
that you could get to it during בין השמשות bein hashmashos *bein
hashmashot*? And it then sort of went from the simple question of
getting to it to well let's say there's only a rabbinic problem.
Well according to Rebbe you can do דרבנן drabbunan *derabbanan*’s בין השמשות
bein hashmashos *bein hashmashot* and therefore that's considered accessible. But then the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* well but in a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *reshut
hayachid* and you're in a רשות הרבים reshus harabim, *reshut harabim* it's
no good. But then it created these virtual realities. So one virtual
reality is everything within four אמות amos *amot* is like it's all
together and it's like it's in the same רשות reshus *reshut* and
how to create a scenario where the עירוב eruv *eruv* was more
than four אמות amos. *amot* away from you. Then the other issue
that came up was you know the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* sort of
spoke about the fact that well maybe you can sort of take
it in stages take it from the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *reshut
hayachid* put it into a כרמלית karmelis, *karmelit* like the arm of
the tree and from the כרמלית karmelis? *karmelit* if that was a
כרמלית Carmelis. *karmelit* take it to you into a רשות הרבים reshus
harabim *reshut harabim*. A lot of what ifs and what ifs you
know. And then the last sort of thing that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* dealt with was if it was in a basket which was
in a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *reshut hayachid* and you're in a
רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut harabim* well you could tip the basket
and it could go in the basket go lower in the basket
like you know and then the basket the bottom of the basket
would be a כרמלית Carmelis *karmelit* and then from there you would
take it to where you are in a רשות הרבים reshus harabim,
*reshut harabim*. So after all of those well you could in theory
do this and in theory do that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* finally
as it were threw up its hands and said then this is
the way I'm describing it why do you ever have to take
the עירוב eruv *eruv* out to anywhere? You should just say well
in theory I'm planning on starting שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* two thousand אמות
*amot* outside of the city. My עירוב eruv. *eruv*'s in my house
but in theory I could have taken my עירוב eruv *eruv* to
my you know to where I wanted it to be. If it
doesn't have to be right in the same space that in theory
I could take it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer was this
is the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* understands I'll tell you what תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafot* says in a minute to make it a little bit
more of a reasonable question. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is
well you know in principle you're right you really shouldn't ever have
to take your עירוב eruv *eruv* out anywhere. But in the case
where you wanted to put an עירוב eruv *eruv* on יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* after שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* יום טוב Yom Tov.
*Yom Tov* on a Sunday there would have been no way to
get your עירוב Eiruv *eruv* where it needs to be on שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* you know for the Sunday because you couldn't move it
on the שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So for that one case we demand
that you always put your עירוב Eiruv, *eruv* out in the right
place. So that's a little crazy. That means that the only reason
you ever have to lay your עירוב Eiruv *eruv* is for a
one case of a יום טוב yontif *Yom Tov* after שבת Shabbos
*Shabbos*. So תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* makes a point which makes the גמרא
Gemara's *Gemara*'s question and answer a little more understandable. תוספות *Tosafot* says
I don't understand the way רש"י Rashi. *Rashi* read the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. In a normal case of an עירוב Eiruv *eruv* on Friday
you can't say well in theory I could bring it to two
thousand אמות *amot* outside the city because when does the עירוב eruv
*eruv* take effect? It takes effect on בין השמשות bein hashmashos. *bein
hashmashot*. So the question is is it accessible to me? is a
question of is it accessible בין השמשות bein hashmashos *bein hashmashot*? So
בין השמשות bein hashmashos, *bein hashmashot* if I'm two thousand אמות *amot*
outside of the city and the עירוב eruv *eruv*'s in my house
I can't bring it to me. First of all it'll take more
time than exists during בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*. בין השמשות *bein hashmashot*
will be over in ten minutes. Number two I can't carry you
know that's a דאורייתא de-oraisa *d'oraisha* carrying it's not a דרבנן *d'rabbanan*
even Rebbe only allows דרבנן *d'rabbanan*s. So that says תוספות *Tosafot* was
never the question. We always understood why you had to actually lay
it on a Friday where it's supposed to be because there's no
way you can carry it during the בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* period
if you know there would be carrying in רשות הרבים reshus harabim.
*reshut harabim* and so on. So תוספות *Tosafot* says the only question
was why do you need to lay the עירוב eruv *eruv* on
יום טוב yontov *Yom Tov*? If you want to put an
עירוב eruv *eruv* let's say on a Wednesday and you wanted to
lay the עירוב eruv *eruv* on Tuesday for Wednesday יום טוב yontov
*Yom Tov* why do you need to do that? Even if it
was בין השמשות *bein hashmashot* about to be יום טוב yontov, *Yom
Tov* you could carry the עירוב eruv *eruv* from wherever it is.
So that was the only question. Why do you need to lay
a יום טוב yontov. עירוב eruv *Yom Tov eruv*? The עירוב eruv
*eruv* could be in your house but in theory in בין השמשות
יום טוב yontov, *bein hashmashot Yom Tov* I could always have carried
it because there's no problem of carrying. So now oh okay that
question already makes sense. יום טוב yontov. *Yom Tov* why do I
need an עירוב eruv *eruv*? And the answer is the only reason
you need an עירוב eruv. *eruv* for יום טוב yontov. *Yom Tov*
to actually put it somewhere is when שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* precedes יום
טוב yontov. *Yom Tov* when יום טוב yontov *Yom Tov* is a
Sunday and then שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* and therefore there's no way you
could have carried it to where it needs to be by Saturday
night. Okay? So that's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s question and answer according
to תוספות *Tosafot* and again it's sort of like the גמרא Gemara's
*Gemara* saying how far are you going to take this what if?
Well in theory I could tip the basket. Alright in theory would
be תוספות *Tosafot*'s phrase you could bring your עירוב eruv *eruv* out
to wherever it needs to be עירוב eruv יום טוב Yom Tov,
בין השמשות יום טוב *eruv Yom Tov bein hashmashot Yom Tov* because
you can carry. So says yeah yeah yeah you're basically right but
it's to cover the case of שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* before יום טוב
*Yom Tov*. Okay now we move on. So while just read the
answer three lines from the top on ל"ד עמוד א' amud aleph
*Lamed Daled amud alef* אמר רבי Rebbi, זירא *Amar Rabbi Zeira*. Yeah,
the only reason you need to lay an עירוב, eruv actually put
it there for a יום טוב, is for the case where שבת
Shabbos precedes יום טוב. Okay, איתיבי. Eisvei. Now I'll ask you on
this idea of the whole sort of basket idea and in theory
you could move it and so on.
נתכוון לשבות ברשות הרבים והניח עירובו בכותל, Nitkaven lishbos b'reshus harabim v'hiniach
eruvo b'kosel, so it's a similar case, you wanted to start your
שבת Shabbos. in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim and instead of putting
your עירוב eruv. in the tree which was a רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid, you put it on a wall. Okay, so if it is
למטה מעשרה טפחים, lemata me'asara t'fachim, it's a low wall and it's
lower than ten טפחים, tefachim, עירובו עירוב, eruvo eruv, obviously it's good.
You're in a רשות הרבים reshus harabim, and the עירוב Eiruv, is
in either רשות הרבים reshus harabim, or a כרמלית, karmelis. but anyway,
you know, according to רבי, Rebbi. fine, that's all okay if you
put it in a wall and it's lower than ten טפחים. tefachim.
למעלה מעשרה טפחים, Lemala me'asara t'fachim, if however the wall is higher
than ten טפחים tefachim and we also assume ארבעה על ארבעה טפחים
arba'a al arba'a t'fachim wide, then אין עירובו עירוב. ein eruvo eruv.
It's not good. This is straight what we taught before. The עירוב
Eiruv is in a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid you're in a רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim. no good, fine, that's just like the tree situation.
Now, another case: נתכוון לשבות בראש השובך או בראש המגדל. Nitkaven lishbos
b'rosh hashovach o b'rosh hamigdal.
Let's say you wanted to start שבת Shabbos not on the ground,
you wanted to start שבת Shabbos on the roof of a chicken
coop
or on the roof of a tower. Now, a מגדל, migdal, as
we'll see, often does not mean like a castle tower, it often
actually meant like some type of a wooden tower, which often was
even portable. Okay, I don't exactly know what they used it for,
yeah, I don't know, it could even have been like almost like
a chest of drawers if you think about it, you know, which
is like ten טפחים tefachim high or so on. Okay, but מגדל
migdal has a can mean different things in terms of how permanent
of a structure it is. You'll see why I'm saying this in
a minute. Anyway, so למעלה מעשרה טפחים עירובו עירוב, lemala me'asara t'fachim
eruvo eruv, למטה מעשרה טפחים אין עירובו עירוב. lemata me'asara t'fachim ein
eruvo eruv. Now רש"י Rashi, has two explanations. You see, not only
are there a lot of תוספות on this דף, but there's a
lot of רש"י.
Rashi I'll give you the second explanation of רש"י, Rashi which is
the easy one.
Here's the street which is a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Here's your
little, you know, tower and you're start now, you're not physically there
by the way. If you're physically there like we said before, then
you don't even need an עירוב. eruv? Okay, but here you are
in the right here you are in your where you want to
start. This is your שובך, shovach, your chicken coop, or your מגדל.
migdal. And here's a wall that runs
right
next to, try to draw like three-dimension, okay, anyway, here's a wall
that runs right along side. Okay, so if you're if the wall
is ten טפחים, tefachim, this is ten טפחים, tefachim, this is a
רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid and if the and if the wall is
ten טפחים tefachim high, it's a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, and if
your עירוב eruv is here, then in theory, assuming that these are
above or against one another, there's no רשות הרבים reshus harabim that
goes in between because then you get into problems of one רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid, to another over רשות הרבים, reshus harabim then your
עירוב eruv you can take it from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to
רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, no problem, it works. Now the question is,
why doesn't it work if it's lower than ten טפחים? tefachim? If
it's lower than ten טפחים, tefachim, you're in a רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid, this would be what, a כרמלית? karmelis So it still would
be like a rabbinic problem, but rabbinic problems maybe are okay according
to רבי. Rabbi, So there are two answers. One answer is, if
the wall is low and usable by the people in the רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim, the wall becomes part of the רשות הרבים. Reshus
HaRabim We had that yesterday. A תשעה טפחים tisha t'fachim wall that's
usable would be a רשות הרבים. Reshus HaRabim. The other answer that
רש"י Rashi gives is, is רש"י Rashi says this isn't considered the
same space. Even though halachically you could access it, you know, the
idea is that the air space of רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim. goes
up to ten טפחים. tefachim. So anything higher than ten טפחים tefachim
is in the same sort of conceptual space, forgetting halachic issues of
accessibility. And if it's lower is in the same, but if you're
higher than עשרה asara and it's lower than עשרה, asara, then it
actually is considered to be in a like different space. Okay, that's
at least
the way רש"י Rashi, explains explains it, but it doesn't fit with
all the גמרא Gemara that seem to not always be bothered by
that idea. But anyway, that's the הלכה halacha here. Okay, so let's
read that again.
נתכוון לשבות בראש השובך או בראש המגדל, Nitkaven lishbos b'rosh hashovach o
b'rosh hamigdal, if you wanted to start שבת Shabbos at the top
of this chicken coop or tower, למעלה מעשרה טפחים lemala me'asara t'fachim
if the עירוב eiruv was higher than ten טפחים tefachim on the
wall, the wall was higher than ten טפחים tefachim and it's right
alongside, עירובו עירוב eruvo eruv it's good, it's accessible, it's one רשות
היחיד Reshus HaYachid to another רשות היחיד, Reshus HaYachid, halachically accessible, physically
accessible. למטה מעשרה טפחים אין עירובו עירוב. Lemata me'asara t'fachim ein eruvo
eruv. Lower it's not, because as I said, either that would make
it from a רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim. to a רשות היחיד, Reshus
HaYachid if it's if the wall becomes part of the רשות הרבים,
reshus harabim or because of רש"י's Rashi idea that it's just considered
to be a different
space. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara
says, ואמאי, V'amai, so if you're doing ואמאי, Ve'amai, in theory you
could tip the basket, why is this a problem? הכא נמי נימא,
Hacha nami neima, what can you tip here? Like you're going to
tip a wall? So here's where the גמרא Gemara strange—strange suggestion. Why
don't we say, הואיל ויכול להטותו ולהביאו לתוך עשרה? Hovil veyachol lehatoso
ulehavio lesoch asara?
So the גמרא Gemara's says, why don't we say that yes, you
actually could tip the מגדל. Migdal. You could tip the tower, because
again the גמרא Gemara. assumes, although it says tower, makes us think
of a big thing, the גמרא Gemara often assumes that a tower
is made out—means a wooden thing, maybe it's even able to think
about it almost like as I said, like a chest of drawers
or maybe here, that would be a good example, like a filing
cabinet. Something like that would be called a מגדל, Migdal, okay? You
got this big filing cabinet or you know, a, you know, dresser,
not dresser, what's it called, a wardrobe, wardrobe, like that would be
like a מגדל. Migdal. So the גמרא Gemara says, I don't get
it, even if it's lower than עשרה טפחים, Asara Tefachim, why don't
I just say in theory I could tip this over, right? And
if I tipped that over, then it would be in a, then
it would be lower than עשרה טפחים Asara Tefachim and it would
be going like from רשות הרבים reshus harabim, to רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. So how far are you going to take this in theory?
Since yesterday we said that even when the עירוב eiruv. was in
a רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid, in the basket, you could tip the
basket over and bring—make—bring it into a כרמלית. karmelis Fine. So this
is the same thing. You're on a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid but
you could tip your, your wardrobe over and put yourself into a
כרמלית karmelis or רשות הרבים. reshus harabim So why should it be
a problem? What's the נפש Nefesh part? Well, okay, you're not physically
there, okay, you're just saying you're starting שבת Shabbos there. Okay. So
that's the גמרא Gemara question. Again, I'm just drawing the person, if
you actually were there you wouldn't need an עירוב, eiruv just to
show you where you're intending to start שבת. Shabbos? Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara is basically trying to, you know, take—do the reductio ad
absurdum of how far you going to say in theory you could
tip and reconfigure things. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי ירמיה,
Amar Rabi Yirmeya, הכא במגדל מסומרת עסקינן. Hacha beMigdal mesumares askinan. Ah,
the, the,
what'd I call it, the wardrobe is nailed into the ground. Okay.
So you can't tip it over. That's why. It's a particular scenario
where physically you can't tip over the wardrobe. Okay. רבא אמר, Rava
amar, אפילו תימא במגדל שאינו מסומר, Afilu teima beMigdal she'eino mesumar,
even if it's not nailed in, הכא במגדל ארוך עסקינן, Hacha beMigdal
aroch askinan,
it's a tall one. So therefore what? דממטי ליה פורתא, Demamtia lei
porta, if you like move it a little bit and you tip
it over, אזיל חוץ לארבע אמות, Azil chutz le'arba amos, then you're
going to wind up, right, if you tip it over, right, then
you're going to wind up outside of—it's not just עשרה טפחים Asara
Tefachim high, of course, you're going to wind up outside of ארבע
אמות. Arba Amos. And if you're outside of ארבע אמות, Arba Amos,
then what? Then number one, you can't bring the עירוב eiruv, to
you because that's ארבע אמות Arba Amos in רשות הרבים. reshus harabim,
And number two, says רש"י, Rashi now of course there's questions about
maybe if you make a lot of little trips, maybe you could
still do it מדרבנן. Miderabbanan. But רש"י Rashi also says, you're ארבע
אמות Arba Amos away, you intended to start שבת Shabbos here. And
if you imagine, well in theory if I virtually tipped it over,
yes, but then you'd be—but then you'd be starting שבת Shabbos. ארבע
אמות Arba Amos away from where you intended to start שבת. Shabbos
So you would not be in the same place you had defined
where your beginning of שבת Shabbos would be, right? Remember we said
you have ארבע אמות Arba Amos in all directions, but if you
had intended to start שבת Shabbos right near the wall and the
only way the עירוב eiruv, is considered accessible is by imagining you
tipped it over, then in practice you're saying that you have to
be starting שבת Shabbos, ארבע אמות Arba Amos away from the wall.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara answer is, look, in some scenarios the
idea that you could tip it over might work, but here for
whatever reason it's physically you can't tip it over, if you tipped
it over you'd be too far away, but yes, we're willing to
say that in theory you could tip it over. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara now keeps on going and saying, you know, if you
did this in theory, in theory I'll give you another what-if or
another in-theory. So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי, Heichi dami, one
minute, what's the case? אי דאיכא כבשא
ומסנא, Ei de'ika kavsa umasna, if there's windows—a window and a rope,
so ליתי בכבשא ומסנא, Leisei bekavsa umasna, why don't you just pull
it with the window—you know through the—you know through—you know through—you know
through the window with the rope? So the גמרא Gemara says, דליכא
כבשא ומסנא, Delieka kavsa umasna, fine, you don't have a window and
a rope. So the גמרא Gemara basic point here is, you know,
I don't get it, says the גמרא. Gemara So don't tip it
over, but I'll give you another what-if. Not a what-if that you'll
tip it over, a what-if, why don't you sort of like, what
if you had a rope tied around here and it's a little
unclear why it says a window, maybe it sort of imagines you're
not literally on top, you're here and you're throwing it through a
window, there's other ways in which תוספות read that, but basically if
you had a rope, why don't we say in theory you could
bring it to you that way? Now of course the question is,
why does the rope make it better? Right? You're still taking it
from—you're in רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, and you're taking it from lower
than עשרה טפחים, Asara Tefachim, how does the rope improve the situation?
So תוספות, one of the answers is is that if you had
a rope attached to it then it would not be considered—you know
we had this whole discussion in שבת Shabbos, about אגד כלי, Eged
kli, if you have something, if you're here and you're רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid, your hand— and part of it is in your house,
okay,
and you have, and you have a basket that goes from your
house into the רשות הרבים reshus harabim and part of it is
in your house and part is in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
that's not considered having carried because part of it remains with you.
So here too if you had a rope attached to it it
would already be considered partly out and therefore moving it fully into
one רשות reshus. would not be, would not be a biblical violation
because it already would have been considered partly in that other רשות.
Anyway, it's another scenario where the גמרא Gemara says a what if
to make things work and again the גמרא Gemara is not willing
to give up on its whole what-if answer or in theory and
says it's a special case, or it's a case where you can't
say this. So again the basic point is yesterday the גמרא Gemara
says even if it's in a basket in רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
it's considered accessible because you could reconfigure it and tip it and
turn it into a כרמלית. karmelis. The גמרא Gemara says if that's
true you could always reconfigure things. You could tip over your tower
and make it into a כרמלית of רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim, You
could have in theory a rope attached to your עירוב eiruv, and
be able to access it that way. And the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer
is yeah you're right, if you could do those things it would
work, but we're talking that you don't have a rope or we're
talking that your tower is nailed down or your tower is very
tall so if you tipped it over it would not be good.
But in theory you would say this what if. Okay, so that
is becomes a very, a very broad definition of accessible, of accessible
in theory even if you would change the configuration. Now thankfully we
move on. Okay, נתנו בבור אפילו עמוק מאה אמה. nasno bebor afilu
amok meiah amah. If you put it in a well even a
hundred אמה amah deep, it's okay. So גמרא Gemara says האי בור
דהיכא. hai bor deheicha. This is going back to the משנה. Mishnah.
Where is this well? אילימא דקאי ברשות היחיד, eileima dekai bereshus hayachid,
if it's in a private domain, meaning the area around it is
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, פשיטא. peshita. Of course, you're in a
רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid right? The area above the well is a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, and the עירוב eiruv is in the bottom
of the well in a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid. so of course
it's good. רשות היחיד עולה עד לרקיע. reshus hayachid oleh ad lerakia.
The same way רשות היחיד reshus hayachid goes up to the heaven,
כי היכי דסלקא לעיל, ki heichi desalka le'eil, the same way it
goes up, הכי נמי דנחית לתחת, hachi nami denachis letachas, it goes
down. So obviously it's a, I mean it's a funny way of
framing it, the בור bor itself is a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid.
but anyway it says of course you and the עירוב eiruv are
in one place, it's accessible, what's the חידוש? chiddush? ואלא דקאי ברשות
הרבים. ve'ela dekai bereshus harabim.
Let's say the בור, bor, the area around the well is a
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim. and so and but the well because it's
ten טפחים tefachim deep is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid היכא קא
ניחא ליה? heicha ka nicha lei? Where are you planning on starting
your שבת? Shabbos, אי למעלה, ei lemala, if you're planning on starting
your שבת Shabbos, on the ground above the well, so we got
a problem. הוא במקום אחד ועירובו במקום אחר. hu bemakom echad ve'eruvo
bemakom acher.
Then you're in one place, רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim and the עירוב
Eruv. is in another. It's at the bottom of the well which
is a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and there's no way you can
get to it on שבת. Shabbos. אלא הוא, ela hu, אי למטה,
ei lemata,
and if you are at the bottom of the well, I mean
not physically but you're planning on starting שבת Shabbos at the bottom
of the well, פשיטא, peshita, then of course it's good. הוא ועירובו
במקום אחד. hu ve'eruvo bemakom echad. You're right there with your עירוב
Eruv? in a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid So what's the issue? So
again what's this whole חידוש chiddush about the well? Either it should
work because you're in רשות הרבים and it's רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
or it's obvious. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא, lo tzricha,
you need it for the case דקאי בכרמלית, dekai bekarmelis, that the
area around the well is a כרמלית and the well itself, the
bottom of the well is a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, and
you wanted to start שבת Shabbos reasonably above the well. So now
you're in a כרמלית and your עירוב is in a רשות היחיד
reshut ha-yachid, that's at the bottom of the well. So you might
think that's no good because rabbinically you can't do that. So again
we go back to what we're saying, ורבי היא, ve'Rabbi hi, this
is the position of רבי, Rabbi דאמר de'amar כל דבר שהוא משום
שבות לא גזרו עליו בין השמשות. kol davar shehu mishum shevus lo
gozru alav bein hashmashos. Anything that's rabbinic does not apply בין השמשות
and therefore like we saw before it's considered accessible even though it's
in a רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid, and you're in a כרמלית. Okay,
so that was just a simple end to the last case in
the משנה Mishnah of the well. But again the point being that
the עירוב has to be considered accessible, accessible means even halakhically accessible,
and רבי Rabbi however is not bothered that it's only a rabbinic
restriction. You could have said that רבי'ס Rabbi's position is a הלכה
halacha in עירוב that it's still considered accessible but the גמרא Gemara
broadens רבי Rabbi with significant halakhic implications to say that really רבי
Rabbi. would allow you to do דרבננס drabbunans during the בין השמשות
period. And then the thing that we spent a lot of time
discussing was what are cases that you could get to it with
only doing a דרבנן and how do you describe what does it
mean in theory you could get to it? How much do you
sort of do the what-ifs and in the in theory and that
was where a lot of the עמוד א' was talking about would
you go so far to say I could change the configuration I
could tip it over and so on. Okay, now we move on
to the next משנה Mishnah
which is a similar application of the previous discussion, let's take a
look. נתנו בראש הקנה או בראש הקונדס. nasno berosh hakaneh o berosh
hakundas. If you put the עירוב at the top of a long
pole. Okay, so the pole isn't a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid. it's
just a pole. It's sticking in the ground and it's a tall
pole and you put it at the top of it. בזמן שהוא
תלוש ונעוץ. bizman shehu talush vena'utz. If it's not— If it's not
a type of a reed that's growing from the ground because קנה
kaneh can mean a reed, then if it was a reed it
would be a problem of using something attached to the ground, but
if it's basically like something that's been detached and is stuck into
the ground, it's a pole. So there's no problem of using it.
אפילו גבוה מאה אמה הרי זה עירוב. Afilu gavoah meah amah harei
zeh eruv. Even a hundred אמות tall, it's an עירוב. Now I
did say that that's a little funny because where how can you
get to it? Forget halakhic issues, it's a hundred אמות. And the
גמרא Gemara doesn't really discuss that. In theory you might have to
say well but I don't know you could shake the pole or
something like that as long as there's not a halakhic problem with
it. But by the way this does indicate the problem that I
mentioned to you about רש״י's Rashi position of higher than ten טפחים
tefachim is never considered the same zone, right? This משנה mishna seems
to go against that because presumably you're on the street of רשות
הרבים, it's on the top of a flag pole. So halakhically it's
accessible but it's still higher than ten טפחים, tefachim, right? It's at
the top of a flag pole. So anyway this indicates that that
would not be a problem. Okay, so it's at the top of
a flag pole, no problem even if it's very high, in theory
maybe you could shake the flag pole and get to it, no
issue. Fine. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. רמי ליה רב
אדא בר מתנא לרבא. Rami lei Rav Adda bar Masna le-Rava. So
רב אדא בר מתנא Rav Adda bar Masna challenged, asked רבא, Rava,
challenged him. תלוש ונעוץ. Talush venautz. In the משנה mishna says it's
only good if it's on top of the flag pole if the
flag pole has been something that was cut down, not like growing
from the ground, you know, it's a קנה, kaneh, and then you
stuck it back in. לא תלוש ונעוץ לא. Lo talush venautz lo.
If it was not the scenario, no, it was just on top
of like a tall קנה kaneh that's growing from the ground, it
would not be good. מאני? Mani? So who would have a problem
if you put it on something growing from the ground? רבנן היא.
Rabanan hi. It's the רבנן Rabbanan who argue on רבי. Rabbi? דאמרי
כל דבר שהוא משום שבות גזרו עליו בין השמשות. De-amri kol davar
shehu mishum shvus gazru alav bein hashmashos. That rabbinic restrictions are a
problem בין השמשות. And therefore they don't want it to be on
a tree or on a קנה kaneh because then it would not
be accessible because that's a rabbinic problem. But the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, what was the whole first משנה? mishna? The whole first
משנה mishna was you put it on what? On a tree! Okay,
so how come this משנה mishna says it can't be growing from
the ground if the first משנה mishna said you could put it
on a tree? ואמרת רישא? Ve-amarta reisha? You said the first משנה
mishna was רבי? Rabbi I mean and you know and the first
משנה mishna explicitly had you putting it on a tree. So the
גמרא Gemara says רישא רבי וסיפא רבנן? Reisha Rabbi vesifa Rabanan? Could
the beginning be the first part be רבי Rabbi and say you
can use a tree, I mean and the end be the רבנן
Rabbanan that say no you can't? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
ליה. Amar lei. So he said back to him. So רבא Rava
said back to him. כדרמי ליה רמי בר חמא לרב חסדא. Kiderami
lei Rami bar Chama le-Rav Chisda. You know you're not the first
one to think of that question. רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama
already asked רב חסדא Rav Chisda this problem. רמי. Rami. רמי Rami
often threw two תנא tannaic sources against one another, like showed the
contradiction of these rabbinic sources. ושיני ליה. Veshani lei. And he answered,
yeah. רישא רבי וסיפא רבנן. Reisha Rabbi vesifa Rabanan. Okay, נו? nu?
So yes the first one goes like רבי Rabbi, that you can
use a tree and the end is רבנן Rabbanan that not. Now
for us that might seem like a very weak answer. But actually
it might you know historically that might really be the answer because
if we remind ourselves that the משניות mishnayos were not written by
רבי, Rabbi? the משניות mishnayos were what by רבי? Rabbi. They were
collated and redacted and edited by רבי. Rabbi So it's coming from
a lot of different sources. So yeah maybe one משנה mishna was
from the school, I mean it's רבי Rabbi. himself the גמרא Gemara
says, but from the school that says you can put an עירוב
on מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka and the fact that rabbinically you cannot
use trees on שבת Shabbos? doesn't prevent it from being a good
עירוב because it's בין השמשות and the whole thing. And the second
source was from a school that said that wouldn't work. Yeah. So
fine the two משניות mishnayos are not from the same school. Okay.
רבינא אמר כולה רבי. Ravina amar kula Rabbi. You know what? It's
all רבי. Rabbi And רבי Rabbi allows you to put it on
a tree but he wouldn't allow you to put it on a
קנה. kaneh. Why not? ושיני ליה רישא—I'm sorry, כולה רבי Rabbi וסיפא
היא וסיפא גזרה שמא יקטום. At the end there's a problem where
afraid that you'll come to to cut it to pick it out
of the ground. Which means although רבי Rabbi says you can do
rabbinic restrictions בין השמשות, he doesn't allow every rabbinic restriction. There are
some things that are much more likely to lead to a דאורייתא
problem that even רבי Rebbe would have to do forbid. So here
don't put your עירוב on something like a—it's essentially like a, you
know, I don't know it's a, it's hard for me even to
imagine what type of a קנה kaneh grows—is sturdy enough to support
the weight of an עירוב. But I don't know. Bamboo? Or maybe—oh
that's interesting—could be bamboo. Or maybe it's like if you imagine like
I don't know like cornstalks or something and it was a light
thing and you put on the top of a cornstalk, something like
that. So there רבי Rebbe is saying there it's not just a
rabbinic restriction of don't use things growing on the ground. The reality
is if we let you do that there's a good chance you'll
come to break off a piece of corn, break off a leaf,
and therefore that I won't go so far to allow that case.
So the reeds case is different than the tree case. Okay, so
that's problem solved number one why it says it can't be מחובר
לקרקע. mechubar l'karka. if until now we were talking about putting them
in trees. Now, the גמרא Gemara has a story. ההוא פומסא, Hahu
Pumsa, a certain army troops. Now, פומסא Pumsa makes you sound of
a certain English word, English word derived from the Latin of polemic,
okay, which means basically an argument, which comes from because פומסא Pumsa
meant troops or an army. Okay, so so, or has to do
with war and army and so on. So a certain army troops
דאתו de'ato לנהרדעא, leNehardea, came to נהרדעא, Nehardea, and they basically were
being quartered in נהרדעא, Nehardea, okay, and they didn't have the constitution
that they wouldn't have to quarter troops. So, and then there was
a problem about where all of this was on שבת, Shabbos where
all of the students were going to go. We had this once
before, you know, that they needed place for the students, they cleared
out a warehouse, they went to the to the you know to
the yards, they went to like the the fields. So this is
often it you we see this scenario where students would get together
with their רבי to learn on שבת, Shabbos? and sometimes they wouldn't
have enough space. So here they didn't have enough space because of
these army troops that were quartered. So אמר להו רב נחמן, Amar
lehu Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to them, them
being presumably his students, פוקו עבידו כבושי כבשי באגמא. Puku avidu kvushey
kavshey be'agma. Today, which was ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, go out and
like lay flat some of the reeds in that like swampy area
over there. I'm pulling's too swampy. But maybe we're going to have
to go sit over there in the field on שבת, Shabbos. okay,
I want you to flatten, let's say it this way, flatten some
of the cornstalks so you'll have a place to sit on שבת,
Shabbos okay, and that's where we're going to do our learning on
שבת. Shabbos. ולמחר Ulemachar tomorrow on שבת Shabbos. ניזיל וניתיב עלויה, Neizal
venesiv alaiy, we'll go and we'll sit on it. איתיביה רמי בר
חמא לרב נחמן, Esvei Rami bar Chama leRav Nachman, so רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama challenged רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, who was saying
that this is what we should do, ואמרי לה רב עוקבא בר
אבא לרב נחמן, Va'amrei lei Rav Ukva bar Abba leRav Nachman, some
say רב עוקבא Rav Ukva challenged רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, תלוש ונעוץ
אין לא תלוש ולא נעוץ לא. Talush venos in, lo talush velo
nos lo. So our משנה Mishnah says that if it's been plucked
out and thrust back in, yes, it's okay to put your עירוב,
but not, not. So what does that mean? So this is, although
a second ago we said that the stalks might be more strict
than the tree, okay, right, and that even רבי who doesn't mind
the tree would mind the stalk. Here, there are, you know, it
sounds they're bothered with I don't understand it, even if you bend
down the corn, let's say we're talking about that, the cornstalks, how
can you sit on the cornstalks? You're not pulling them out of
the ground. You'll still be sitting on the cornstalks bent over that
are attached to the ground. That should be like using something growing
from the ground like sitting on a tree, which you're not allowed
to do. And you see in the משנה Mishnah that the stalks
are just like the tree, because it says you can't have your
עירוב on a stalk. So again, a minute ago we said the
stalks are even worse than the tree, but here רב נחמן Rav
Nachman seemed to not be bothered by using stalks on שבת Shabbos,
and sitting on stalks. So they said why you're not bothered by
sitting on stalks on שבת? Shabbos. That should be as bad as
using the tree. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara. answer is.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, התם בעוזרדין, Hatam
be'ozardin, that's a case of עוזרדין ozardin which is that the stalks
are already hardened, they're not very flexible. And because they're hardened, they're
more like the tree, either just in terms of categorically we would
see it more tree-like because it's stiff, or because of the rabbinic
concern that you'll come to pluck it off. Something that's very flexible
and pliable, there's less of a chance, there's almost like less of
a chance that you'll pick a piece of a grass than there
is that you'll pluck off, you know, that you'll snap off a
branch because if something is harder it snaps, it's easier to break
and maybe you're more inclined to break it off. So he says,
yeah, you know when the reeds are a problem? It's when they're
hard and they're tree-like. But when they're soft, it's like grass and
that doesn't is not in the same category of not using a
tree. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's see
if it likes that answer. ומנא תימא דשאני לן בין עוזרדין לשאינו
עוזרדין? Umina teima deshany lan bein ozardin leshe'eino ozardin? How do I
know that there's a distinction between whether they are hardened or not
hardened, that only when they're hardened are they tree-like and therefore forbidden?
דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא. Beraita. Now this is less
about the rabbinic concern that you'll break it off and more about
a formal category of you put things in a category in a
in a tree category or in a vegetable category. And we're going
to look at the laws of כלאים kilayim of how you categorize
it. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Beraita, הקנים והאטדים וההיגים,
Hakanim veha'atadim veha'ahigim, which is basically like stalks and אטדים atadim and
היגים higim are more like sort of like thornbushes. מין אילן הן,
Min ilan hein, they're all considered trees, ואינם כלאים בכרם, Ve'einam kilayim
bakerem, and it's not a problem planting them in a vineyard. You
cannot mix vine seeds, vine, with wheat, with grain, with vegetable, but
you can actually plant trees alongside vines. So all of these bushes
and these קנים, kanim, these reeds, are considered like trees. So here
you see one way we categorize reeds is in the tree category.
דתניא אידך, Detanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא, Beraita, הקנים, Hakanim,
the same reeds. והכידן vehakidan והעורבנין veha-urbanin and these other two things
and which רש״י Rashi gives some word for, what does it say
there in שטיינזלץ, Steinsaltz, so are these these things, so looking, bull
rushes, cassia, this is the second list? Second list, yeah, yeah, boxthorn
is in the first list. Okay, but anyway this list is what?
Bull rushes? Okay, also cassia. Anyway, some type of thing, some type
of thing that's grown from the ground. All of these things are
מין ירקין, min yerakin, are considered in the vegetable category or if
you want like the grass and the vegetable category then כלאים kila'im
becomes is a problem with the vines. So now we've got a
problem. Are the reeds in the tree category or in the vegetable
category? Because it's mentioned in both lists. קשיא אהדדי, kashya adadi, it's
contradicting itself. אלא שמע מינה, ela shema mina, so you see the
resolution is כאן בזורדין כאן בשאינו זורדין, kan be-zardin kan be-she'eino zardin,
it depends whether they're hardened or not. שמע מינה shema mina you
see it. So basically, again, this is why you see sometimes it's
very interesting right? When does a גמרא Gemara get to the root
of what the concern is? And when does it and what what
the root, I was really no pun intended that. And when does
it deal with just formal definitions? Trees versus non-trees. So the concern
of using a tree on שבת is you'll come to break off
a twig. Okay, so what's in the tree category? Maybe you want
to put everything that has that concern that you'll break off a
twig and that should be your guiding principle. But the fact that
the גמרא Gemara quotes a discussion in כלאים, kila'im, what does כלאים
kila'im have to do with using a tree on שבת? Nothing in
terms of the reason. The only way you make the comparison is
you say we're going to use once we've said don't use trees,
now what does how is a tree defined? So it has nothing
to do with what the motivating reason was behind it. We're going
to look in other areas of הלכה Halacha and use that definition
of tree. Okay? And therefore we can go to כלאים kila'im because
we're going to take just the formal definition of tree and we're
also going to assume that that formal definition will apply across categories.
So that's always very interesting to see how often does the תורה
Torah have local definitions or does it use general definitions and is
it a formalist type of an approach or is it an approach
that gets to the core reason? But here this is the answer
his approach, that it is a formal approach and soft reeds are
in the vegetable category not the tree category and therefore you can
use them on שבת. And the only problem not pick them, but
use them, sit on them. The only problem is the משנה Mishnah
was when it was a hardened reed and in the tree category.
Yes, Michael. Two questions. One is okay, so even if it's soft
we're not worried that maybe somehow it'll get uprooted? Yeah, so that's
the point again, same type of issue that the Rabbis only made
their תקנה takkanah with certain parameters. No, but I'm saying but I
understand that like you know but it should still be the same
idea. In other words I understand, but that so that's a good
question. Why didn't they apply things like in a broader way? But
you know, we should be happy they didn't in the sense that
you could always say, well, like the גמרא Gemara before, what if
this, what if this, what if that, so you have to give
some certain limits to it and some certain parameters and we see
we have all these very specific cases, like you know, I wanted
to make my שביתה shevitah at the bottom of this pit, top
of this let's say I just said just in the pit. Is
that okay or does it like really have to be specific? Yeah,
like in the pit. Yeah, I don't know. Look, I thought the
general question is why would I anyway ever assume that the guy
didn't want to make his שביתה shevitah in the exact place where
he put the עירוב? Why wouldn't so maybe we do, you know,
it's a good question about what if he didn't have particular כוונה
kavannah or what if he had sort of generic כוונה. kavannah. I'll
have to I'll have to get back on that. Yeah, Charlie. There
we don't seem to be consistent on whether we're willing to apply
categorizations from one area of הלכה Halacha to another. Correct. We are
not consistent. In every different סוגיא sugya you have to see whether
what one of the classic חקירות chakiras that רב חיים Reb Chaim
asks is, is this a דין מסוים din mesuyam or a דין
כללי. din klali. He doesn't use the phrase דין כללי din klali
but he does use the phrase I think דין מסוים din mesuyam
which basically means is this category a local category or a universal
category? And that really is different in every סוגיא sugya and the
key tip off is if or you know or the key evidence
is are they bringing definitions from other areas of הלכה? Halacha? And
then you see that the גמרא Gemara is being completely formalist about
it and using a more assuming a sort of a universal category
and that's exactly what you see here. Yeah. It seems a little
more complicated in the sense they're not talking about certain reeds which
are hard and certain reeds which are soft, it's the same reed
over the course of its growth hardens. Right. I'm sorry if I
didn't make that clear. That is correct. Yes. So it's but that
when the reed has hardened how soft it is. Yeah, but you
can see, I mean, you know, some things are very obvious, have
they which stage they've gotten to, how pliable they are. But thank
you, if I didn't make that clear. Yes. The distinction here is
not different types of reeds, it's whether the reed has hardened yet
or not hardened yet. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara just wraps
this up. קידה מין ירקא, kida min yeraka, one of the things
we mentioned that counted as a vegetable for כלאים kila'im purposes was
קידה. kida. And that's actually in the in the תורה. Torah. So
some type of aromatic right you know spice or plant. How do
they translate it? Cassia. Cassia. Cassia. Okay, does anybody... know about that
thing? Is it aromatic? Anybody have any? Like a very coarse cinnamon
bark. Okay, cinnamon is interesting. Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says, is that really true that that's in the
vegetable category? דהא תנן, De-ha tnan, we learned in the משנה, Mishnah,
אין מרכיבין Ein markivin פגם pgam אגבי agabi קידה לבנה. kida levana.
You don't graft פגם, pgam, whatever that is. What do they say
פגם pgam is? Rue? Rue, yeah. What? רש"י Rashi says רודא ruda
or whatever it's a picture of it. Rue. Okay. I thought it
was something you don't want to do, like I rue the day.
Right. You don't graft rue on this white קידה. kida. מפני שהוא
ירק באילן, Mipnei she-hu yerek be-ilan, because the rue is a vegetable
and this white קידה kida is in the tree category. So although
you can have trees in your vineyard, you can't cross-breed trees with
vegetables. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you see again this קידה
kida seems to be in the tree category. אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Papa, קידה לחוד וקידה לבנה לחוד. Kida le-chud ve-kida levana le-chud.
There's a difference between קידה kida and white קידה. kida. קידה kida
is in the vegetable category, white קידה kida is in the tree
category. Okay, so this thing might change, variations on a certain type
of a plant or as we see even in a plant's life,
from soft to hard, going to whether it is considered a vegetable
or a tree. Actually, you know, it's a good point because given
that according to רש"י it is the same thing at a later
part in its life, it's pretty funny that the משנה Mishnah should
say that it's not a problem having it in the vineyard, since
it would be a problem having it grow in the vineyard because
it goes first through the soft stage before it gets to the
hard stage. So what good does it do saying in the hard
stage it's not a problem being in the vineyard if it could...
maybe, ah, maybe it grew first, got to the hard stage, and
now you want to plant some vines. That would be the scenario,
yes.
Applying the different stages of life of something that is alive, this
is an issue for whether swordfish would be כשר kosher or
not.
Ha, interesting question, right, but how do you look at things that
have certain qualities at various stages? Right. Okay, let's take a look
at the next, I mean obviously, like your point, I don't assume
the criteria are the same, you know, but it's an analogous type
of a discussion. Okay, let's look at the next משנה. Mishnah. Now
we get to, interesting, so that was issues about like רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid רשות הרבים, using מחובר. mechubar. We actually have being on
top of the pole, as I mentioned, seems to indicate that if
it's even your, like, this idea of רש"י before, not being one
above עשרה טפחים asara tefachim and the other below seems this משנה
Mishnah seems very clearly not saying that, that it could be at
top of a pole and you could be on רשות הרבים. Fine.
So we've dealt with those cases. Those are mostly הלכה halacha issues
about can you get to it for הלכה halacha reasons and even
on top of the pole we said maybe you'd have to be
able to like shake the pole and have it fall down. What
if you can't access it not because of הלכה halacha reasons but
because of practical reasons? It's not physically accessible. So that's what this
next משנה Mishnah turns to, but we will see there might be
הלכה halacha points here as well. נתנו במגדל, Netano be-migdal, you put
it again in this מגדל, migdal, which we're saying for argument's sake
is something like a wardrobe, okay, ואבד המפתח, ve-avad ha-mafte'ach, and you
lost the key. You locked it up into your chest, into the
wardrobe, and you lost the key. Is it a good עירוב for
שבת or not? Because you can't get to it. Forget הלכה, halacha,
you can't get to
it. הרי זה עירוב, Harei zeh eruv, it's good. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, אם אינו יודע שהמפתח במקומו אינו עירוב. im eino
yodei'a she-ha-mafte'ach bi-mekomo eino eruv. If you don't know that the key
is where it's supposed to be, it's not good. Now in the
משנה Mishnah you might think that the whole
debate is...
right, it could
be misplaced, you don't know. Right, well, we'll discuss in the גמרא
Gemara what happens if you find it on שבת. Okay, so anyway,
but you could have said in the משנה Mishnah that maybe the
whole debate is, maybe the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma doesn't care that
it's not physically accessible, as long as like there's no הלכה halacha
barrier, it's pretty funny, like הלכה halacha creates a greater reality than
the physical world. So if there's a הלכה halacha barrier, it's not
considered accessible. If it's only a physical problem, that is accessible, that
is מקום אחד, makom echad, let's call it. Maybe it's more of
a concept of being במקום אחד. be-makom echad. So just because there's
a physical problem doesn't make it in a different מקום. makom. הלכה
halacha sort of רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, רשות הרבים does. But the
גמרא Gemara is going to assume that even according to the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma you have to physically be able to access it
and is going to discuss how you can do that. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Yes, you have a question?
Yes.
This is for your עירוב תחומין, eruv techumin, right? So you've got
this closet out
in the 2,000...
that we're talking about...
Yes, you're right. I don't exactly know how the scenario is that
it's out there in the middle of the field, this closet standing
there. But you put it there because you didn't want somebody to
steal your עירוב and there you locked it.
But then you're locked out. Right. But how do you carry the
key?
Oh, you've got that stuck with that metallic thing underneath the bottom.
But no, but
I think that's why the משנה Mishnah says במקומו, bi-mekomo, that the
מפתח mafte'ach is in its place because you're right, if even if
you didn't lose the key, if you had no way to get
the
key...
What does that mean if אינו יודע שהמפתח במקומו bimkomo *eino yodeiah
she-ha-mafteiach bimkomo*?
That's if you don't know that the key is where it's supposed
to be, meaning if you don't know where the key is, it's
a funny way of saying it. But he is saying it, he's
basically saying if you don't know where the key is, then it's
a problem. But he might be saying the במקומו *bimkomo* point because
of what I just said, that maybe the key may have to
be there, has to be accessible where that is. If the key
is somewhere else and you can't carry the key to the to
the closet, it's not going to be any good either. Okay.
How about like that happens to us all the time where you
know you put it away, but you forget where you put it?
Right. So that's presumably not good. That's אינו יודע *eino yodeiah*. You
don't know. Right. Yeah. Yeah. It's basically a way of saying if
the key is lost, but it's funny that he used so many
words to say that.
But why is that different from the first?
It's not. He's just saying it's not good. The תנא קמא tanna
kamma. *Tanna Kamma* says it is good. תנא קמא tanna kamma *Tanna
Kamma* says הרי זה עירוב harei zeh eiruv. *harei zeh eiruv* and
he says אינו עירוב *eino eiruv*. Okay. All right. So let's take
a look at גמרא *Gemara*. ואמאי *ve-amai*? Why is it good according
to the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*? הוא במקום אחד ועירוב במקום אחר
*hu bemakom echad ve-eiruv bemakom acher*. It's considered a different place even
just if it's physically inaccessible the same way הלכתית *halachically* makes it
a different place physically inaccessible makes it a different place even according
to the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*. So רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו *Rav
u-Shmuel de-amri tarveihu*, רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* both say הכא במגדל
של לבנים עסקינן *hacha bemigdal shel leveinim askinan*. We're talking about that
it's not made out of wood. It's made out of bricks. Okay.
That should seem to be harder. ורבי מאיר היא דאמר פוחת לכתחילה
*ve-Rabbi Meir hi de-amar pocheis le-chatchilah*. And according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* that says you could actually deconstruct a something made
out of bricks. Again,
without plaster. It's right. Without plaster. It's just bricks that are laid
on top of one another. And you actually can take it apart
and it's not considered סותר *soser* on שבת *Shabbos*, which is pretty
amazing. Because you would think that if, you know, if it creates
a real structure and also like the weight of the bricks are
pushing down the lower bricks, it's not like something that is like
completely temporary. But actually there's a position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* that if there's no binding agent and they're just piled,
it's not considered סותר *soser* to undo it on שבת *Shabbos*.
So according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*, I could deconstruct
one of these stone walls in New England that've been there for
400 years?
Right. I was actually thinking exactly of that because I remember, I
don't remember what the context was but I remember when we discussed
a similar thing earlier, you know, when we were learning שבת *Shabbos*,
either you or Dov who said, you know, that they that, you
know, that they
have this way of doing it without plaster, you know, that lasts
for hundreds of years. I guess it's real art of the way
you fit the stones together and they can exist for hundreds of
years. Yeah, I know. So it's shocking. So let's take a look.
But maybe here's maybe why it says לבנים *leveinim*. לבנים *leveinim* are
bricks. They're not stones. So maybe actually stones would be different. If
because with stones, because of the different sizes, you can actually create
like a more permanent type of a fit. But bricks, you know,
are just are you know there's no they don't like they don't
interlock. So therefore, so maybe that's specifically bricks and not stones.
And bricks can easily break, they crumble.
Well that's true. But anyway, but that's why maybe it's specifically bricks
and not stones. So let's see what he says. דאמר פוחת לכתחילה
ונוטל *de-amar pocheis le-chatchilah ve-notel*. That you can undo it and take
from the meaning in a case where a different case. What was
the case? דתנן *de-tenan*, we taught in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*, בית
שמילאו פירות סתום *bayis she-millao peiros satum*. You have a house that
it's filled with vegetables, it's or fruit, it's your storehouse and it's
sealed. Okay. There's no you know you threw away the key or
whatever it is. It's you know you sealed the door. ונפחת *ve-nifchat*.
Now let's say the wall crumbled or you know opened up. נוטל
ממקום הפחת *notel mi-makom ha-pachas*. You can take the fruit from where
you know there's a breach in the wall and it's like not
a מוקצה *muktzah* concern even though it was sealed in this house
before שבת *Shabbos* or actually it's יום טוב *Yom Tov* before יום
טוב *Yom Tov* began. It's a משנה mishna *Mishnah* from ביצה *Beitzah*.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אומר *Rabbi Meir omer*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
says, פוחת ונוטל לכתחילה *pocheis ve-notel le-chatchilah*. You can even undo the
wall לכתחילה *le-chatchilah*. So you see that according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, if it's just laid with bricks, you can actually take it
apart. So our משנה mishna *Mishnah* would be talking that it's
in some house.
Right. Or it's crazy. I know. It's wild. So our משנה mishna
*Mishnah* would be talking that it's in a chest, it's in a
wardrobe made out of laid bricks, and according to the תנא קמא
*Tanna Kamma*, it's considered to be accessible. Okay. So now the גמרא
*Gemara* continues. ואמר רב נחמן בר אדא אמר שמואל באווירא דלבני *ve-amar
Rav Nachman bar Ada amar Shmuel ba-avira de-livni*. הכא *hacha*. So one
minute. But והאמר *ve-ha-amar*, excuse me, isn't a question. והאמר *ve-ha-amar* it's
it's sometimes והאמר *ve-ha-amar* is a statement, at least the way רש"י
*Rashi* reads it. So or maybe it's a question. How can you
say it talks about any bricks or anything? Doesn't רב נחמן בר
אדא *Rav Nachman bar Ada* say in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*
באווירא דלבני *ba-avira de-livni*? Now רש"י *Rashi* says all באווירא דלבני *ba-avira
de-livni* means is this thing which is like basically bricks that are
just, you know, like laid on top of one another. Meaning without
plaster. So the גמרא *Gemara* says fine. הכא נמי באווירא דלבני *hacha
nami ba-avira de-livni*. Here too, that's what we mean. So just clarifying
it would be a case of bricks that are laid one on
another, no plaster. And according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, you can
actually undo it on שבת *Shabbos*. So now the גמרא *Gemara* says,
ואמר רב זירא ביום טוב beyontov. אמרו *ve-amar Rav Zeira be-Yom Tov
amru*. One minute. רב זירא *Rav Zeira* says it's only on יום
טוב *Yom Tov*. אבל לא בשבת *aval lo be-Shabbos*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* wouldn't allow it on שבת *Shabbos*, which is funny because there's
no difference in terms of the מלאכה *melachah* of סותר *soser* by
שבת *Shabbos* and יום טוב *Yom Tov*. But what it's maybe it
has to do with שמחת יום טוב *simchas Yom Tov*. You know,
sometimes they allow more things. things to give you access to food
on יום טוב, particularly the תורה Torah says, you know, אך אשר
יאכל לכל נפש. ach asher yei'achel lechol nefesh. So even though you
can't go ahead and build a house or destroy a house to
get food, but meaning but at רבי מאיר maybe it was a
special יום טוב leniency. So הכא נמי ביום טוב. hacha nami beyontov.
So גמרא says, okay, הכא נמי ביום טוב. hacha nami beyontov. Our
משנה Mishnah. is talking about יום טוב when it's in the our
משנה Mishnah, about the עירוב is a יום טוב case. So גמרא
says אי הכי, i hachi, one minute. That's true, היינו דתניא עלה,
haynu detanya ala, we had a ברייתא braisa exactly on this משנה
Mishnah. that says the following. רבי אליעזר אומר אם בעיר אבד עירובו
עירוב ואם בשדה אבד אין עירובו עירוב. Rabbi Eliezer omer im ba'ir
avad eiruvo eiruv ve-im basadeh avad ein eiruvo eiruv. So this is
exactly the question that you raised, getting the key to where it
is. Okay. So he says, if it's in the if it's in
the but here it's talking about it's lost. If it's lost in
the city, then the key, then it's an עירוב. Because then you
can get it to because assuming it assumes again, the question is,
you know, how do you get it out there because it's outside
of the if it's in the city, if it's in the city,
so there's a lot of houses and there's a lot of walled
courtyards and the assumption is that wherever you find the key, you
can take it from a walled courtyard, you know, onto into the
next walled courtyard, maybe travel up by the roofs, you know, and
there's like it's you can travel very far through רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid? Now the question still is that, you know, okay, but obviously
your עירוב is outside of the city limit. So it's very strange
it would have to assume look, you could have structures outside of
the city limit that are not considered houses. Nobody lives in them,
they're like warehouses. So you'd have to assume a scenario that you
could sort of do it, you know, or maybe there are walled
fields, you know, that you can get it out there or something.
So the גמרא isn't fully explaining but basically it means if your
key is lost in the city, so in theory if you find
it, you could somehow carry it through various רשות היחיד and get
it to your עירוב, then it counts. Even though it's lost, this
is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who's I'm sorry.
So so one minute let's take a look. Let's read this. אם
בעיר im ba'ir so this רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in the משנה
said if you lost the key it's not good. Here in the
ברייתא braisa he explains the following. אם בעיר אבד im ba'ir avad
it depends. If it's lost in the city, then עירובו עירוב. eiruvo
eiruv. It'll be good because I could say maybe you'll find your
key and you'll be able to get it to you'll be able
to get it to where to where you need it. ואם בשדה
אבד, ve-im basadeh avad, however, if you lost it in the field,
then even if you found your key, there would be no way
you could get it to your עירוב, to the then אין עירובו
עירוב. ein eiruvo eiruv. It's not good. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
who says it's not good, we find out in the ברייתא braisa
he's not so מחמיר. machmir. He doesn't say if it's lost end
of story. He says if it's lost in a place that even
were you to find it, you couldn't get it then it's to
the to the עירוב, then it's no good. So now the גמרא
says we can't be talking about יום טוב, because here he's concerned
about carrying the key, right? So obviously we're not talking about יום
טוב. So the גמרא says ואי ביום טוב, ve-i beyontov, if the
case was a יום טוב, מאי לי עיר מאי לי שדה? mai
li ir mai li sadeh? What do I care whether it's a
city or a field? So the גמרא says חסורי מחסרא hachi soraei
machsoraei top of ל"ה lamed heh
we'll just read this answer.
It's missing some words, והכי קתני, vehachi katani, and this is how
you have to read it. נתנו במגדל ונעל בפניו ואבד המפתח. nasano
be-migdal veno'al befanav ve-avad hamafte'ach.
So he put it in the chest and he locked it and
it was lost. הרי זה עירוב. That is good. That's the תנא
קמא. Now why is it good? So the גמרא's answer it's good
is because it's made out of bricks and you can take apart
the bricks on שבת. But the מאן דאמר man d'amar when is
it good? ביום טוב. Because taking apart the bricks that רבי מאיר
allowed is only a he only allowed taking apart the bricks on
יום טוב. So when is that good? That's on יום טוב. אבל
בשבת, aval be-Shabbos, but if it was locked in the wardrobe on
שבת, even if it was out of the bricks, אין עירובו עירוב,
ein eiruvo eiruv, it would not be good. נמצא המפתח, nimtza hamafte'ach,
if the key was found, בין בעיר בין בשדה, bein ba'ir bein
basadeh, אין עירובו עירוב, ein eiruvo eiruv,
whether in the field or in the city, it would not be
good. Now why would it not be good if it was found
in the city, if you can get it to where, you know,
to where the עירוב is? So I'll get back to that in
a minute, but let's just finish how we're re-reading the ברייתא. braisa.
רבי אליעזר אומר בעיר עירובו עירוב. Rabbi Eliezer omer ba'ir eiruvo eiruv.
In the city it is good because you can get it to
where the עירוב is. בשדה אין עירובו עירוב. basadeh ein eiruvo eiruv.
And in the field it is not good. So this is actually
now the גמרא goes from where did you lose it to where
did you find it. Okay. So let's just take a step back
because I think it's getting a little confusing. The first question is
the תנא קמא says if it's locked up it's good. Why is
it good? You can't get to it. So the גמרא's going to
give more answers to that question yesterday tomorrow, but today yesterday in
our time machine tomorrow we'll have more answers to why is it
good if it's locked up, but our answer today that it's good
if it's locked up is it's in one of these it's in
a brick sort of construction where you can where you can according
to רבי מאיר you can undo it if it's יום טוב. So
our case is talking about יום טוב and about laid bricks and
therefore it's good on on and not on שבת. And therefore it's
considered accessible. That answers question number one why is it good. In
the משנה. But now we turn to this other question about where
is the key. So we had a ברייתא Baraita that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer said if the key is lost in the city, then
actually it's okay. If it's lost in the field, it's no good.
Which seems to be that the possibility of finding the key is
enough to make it good, but only if, assuming if you found
the key, you could get it to the עירוב. Now that the
גמרא is re-reading the משנה, the גמרא's actually shifting a little bit.
It's not saying where you lost the key. If it's still lost,
maybe it's a problem, but you actually found the key. Okay, so
you found the key. If you found it in the city versus
the field. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer still makes this difference: city versus
field.
He says במקומו over the משנה.
I know, let's just finish with this. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer makes
a distinction again between city and the field. Did you find it
in a place you could get it to, or not in a
place, or a place you can't get it to? And חכמים Chachamim
say even if you find it in the city, it's no good.
Why even if you find it in the city it's no good?
So here the argument, the idea is, and we've seen this before,
this idea that you can carry from a roof to a courtyard
and from a courtyard to another roof, and from that to another
walled-in thing, all even though it's all רשות היחיד, those are considered
according to some opinions different רשויות. reshuyos. All roofs are one thing,
all courtyards are one thing, but you can't go from a roof
to a courtyard or a courtyard to a roof. So the debate
here then becomes a question of, even if you found it in
the city, could you get it all the way out to where
you needed to get it by traveling through different רשות היחיד? Okay,
so we'll continue tomorrow, but again the upshot is that why is
it considered accessible? It's a special case of bricks according to רבי
מאיר on יום טוב, but then the more interesting question that we're
now turning to is—I think more interesting—is the question about where was
the key lost, where was it found, is the possibility of finding
the key enough to say it's accessible, and this issue about how
can you get it, you know, can you get your key to
the עירוב? So more on this tomorrow.